today is really an experiment in whether
we can find new ways to all understand
one another rebel wisdom is an evolving
conversation the main topics of it are
the challenge of sense making the the
sense that our sense making institutions
are breaking down at an ever-increasing
rate this sense that there are a lot of
neglected perspectives and ideas and
also the that that a lot of the way that
we've run society is breaking down and
these I we need to find new ideas from
somewhere this is something I think is
being increasingly obvious to all of us
that something about society is is off
and being increasingly recognized that
it's off and the only way out is to to
bring in some new ideas some of the
ideas that have been sort of on the
fringe of the culture and have never
been part of the culture and we're very
lucky that some of the speakers are
bringing the speakers we have here are
bringing some of those perspectives
we're poised in a way for catastrophe or
transformation and I think that is
becoming more and more clear and I think
a lot of people are intuitive that and
there's very different ways that that
that that's showing up and there's
different narrative about how that's
showing up but I think we all sense that
something shifting an old way is coming
to an end and something new could be
born as a journalist I'm very familiar
and driven by this idea of speaking
truth to power in the social media age a
lot of this power is kind of distributed
its its social shaming it's the power of
the mob it's the power of not being able
to to say certain things how do we think
in public if every time we sort of don't
express ourselves perfectly or we don't
give enough context that we're attacked
and we kind of learn not to say certain
things so this there is something that
needs to happen with this kind of
increased polarization especially driven
by social media that we need to create
spaces to have these conversations that
we feel that we're not able to express
and to make mistakes and to say things
wrong to be challenged and to to not
feel that that is going to be
career ending there is a what the ideas
that we need to talk about for sure
there's a definite what to be described
but the how is as important the how is
why we're here
is this event it's not enough to come
out these problems intellectually it
just doesn't work we need to come at it
with an understanding of that physiology
and so there's a few useful models one
is polyvagal theory which talks about
the vagus nerve and its role in our
nervous systems role in effectively
putting us into either a defensive mode
where we feel under threat and we shut
down we start thinking differently we're
less open to new ideas and we're really
defending ourselves and that that you
know we can see that when we fall into
an ideological position or a really
fixed position it's like not I'm not
budging it's not safe to budge so we
need to understand how we can let's say
hack our bodies and come into a more
relaxed exploratory mode and that's why
we're also going to be using some
techniques today to help us get into
that mode help us relax help us activate
our parasympathetic nervous system which
is the rest and digest is the opposite
of the sympathetic nervous system where
we're feeling in fight or flight or
freeze and we know that from that space
for the fight-or-flight we can have a
productive generative conversation it
just doesn't work we have to get into a
space of relaxation and curiosity
there's also another really key term
we're not entirely sure in that space
what the answer is
I just like to ask you each to talk for
a couple of minutes about what you want
to achieve it's a little hard to put my
finger on but I do think based on what
I've seen over the last two years that
there is some sort of a reorganization
of alliances there's an awakening
happening and a change in allegiances
where people are realizing that those
that have traditionally been their
allies may not be natural allies and the
people that they have viewed with
suspicion may be closer to them than
they had expected the problem is in
order for those alliances to function
you have to learn how people on the
other side of them actually think and
this is very perilous the remedy
involves us talking to each other enough
that we begin to understand what the
other person's cognitive model is and I
see the hope for bootstrapping our way
out of the predicament that we humans
are in that hope arises from our hearing
each other enough to develop a shared
model that will allow us to say
provocative things that are true and
then act on the basis of that we all
could use more humanizing of each other
we are we're all someone's deplorable
and probably right
if you describe any brief brief ideology
to which we appear to subscribe and I
think the greatest failures in
communication happen when we have
allowed those ideas about each other to
get in the way of actually remembering
that every single person that we
interact with is just as human and
sometimes brave and sometimes scared and
sometimes certain and sometimes quite
uncertain as the being that you are in
your own head every single one of us and
what I have seen is the biggest failures
of communication
bethey when mod rule came to our campus
it was clear that there was dehumanizing
that happened first so the more
conversations we can have in which we
look people in the eyes and learn learn
the human on the other side the more
likely we are to be able to take that
out into the world and not view anyone
no matter what their views may be as
caricature first would be a hope that we
can each of us be supported and
discovering more deeply and be brought
into more insight into that aspect of
the larger story of the desires
specifically to hold and to be renewed
in our hope in the context of that
larger story and then perhaps as the day
revolves perhaps feeling a sense of
there being an insight that is larger
than ourselves that is also present I
would like to see people go away feeling
a little more confident in being able to
close reports a little I think it's
extraordinary that when I was growing up
and I'm much older than anybody in the
50s and 60s it seemed to me that we were
entering an era in which there was
enormous freedom and dig it was and and
it's rather paradoxical that we now find
ourselves in one of the more constrained
intellectual environments I never saw
this coming and I think that being able
to take an unpopular position should be
something we can all do without fear of
being dehumanized I think there's
nothing that cannot be said it's the way
in which it said so I don't think we
should censor content I think we should
send some manner and I think that
everything can be said as long as people
say it in a respect
away and one of my very strong beliefs
is competition is certainly part of the
history of all life but equally
important or I would say more about this
collaboration and that actually all life
is a matter of collaboration your body
is a lot of bacteria that decided
altruistically to get together and serve
a common purpose everything that is
living does so because it collaborates
and I would like us to be able to
collaborate on things that are true and
beautiful and if we do that we actually
might get ourselves out of the hole we
dug ourselves into it's important to get
people into smaller groups because we
have 150 people here attending the
summit and in a group of that size it's
really difficult to create that level of
intimacy and connection and
understanding that you get in a smaller
group of say 10 where we can really get
a sense of even in a day we can get a
sense of the other people in the group
we can get a sense of what they're
bringing who they are and we build a
certain trust and a word we use as
coherence where we're a little bit more
of a coherence with one another I
understand what you're saying you
understand what I'm saying you might not
agree with me but at least we're meeting
each other as human beings
so so on one level of surround intimacy
and the other level that's around it's
much easier to have a conversation the
smaller the group gets as Ali said we
spent the morning building building up
to what we're going to do now sort of
got to know each other a little bit in
our small groups and made some
connections and that's to build up the
the safety and the connection to do what
we're going to do now and we talked
about before about sort of feeling how
feelings stifled around certain topics
and certain things that were allowed to
express and we're not allowed to express
certainly kind of made much worse by the
kind of low bandwidth of social media is
a real is a real issue that thinking in
public has become very dangerous because
things can be taken out of context and
for that reason we are going to turn the
cameras off now
we shut off the cameras in the main room
because the invitation to the speakers
and everyone else was to have a
conversation around things we don't feel
comfortable talking about in public and
that felt much easier to do with the
cameras off so right now that's exactly
what everyone's doing here the speakers
modeled that up on stage and they
discussed a variety of topics that
aren't really we're not able to discuss
easily in public either through social
pressure or because there are quite
complex but but mainly because we're
stifled in some sense by a mob mentality
that we're afraid to activate in order
to really kind of reach truth with one
another we have to kind of take that
risk to not really have a fully-formed
idea to not quite know the you know have
a sense of something but not quite there
and also to be able to keep a balance in
ourselves of monitoring our own
responses and reactions so that we can
be calm we can listen properly even if
we're talking about or listening to a
really challenging idea that that might
be so different to what we think
topics the speakers were you know they
got a heavy territory which is great and
a lot to reflect on and I'm I'm
motivated you know without that sense of
panic so that that healthy sense of
urgency leaving this session today it's
been great for giving people a real
sense of community and and hope figuring
out how to talk to each other with
generosity and enough precision to
convey something important is one of the
bigger questions of our age we nominally
share a language but because of the way
we live that language is a blunt
instrument and so events like this that
caused people to look at how they are
communicating what it is that they
convey and in what way they might reach
across unbridgeable gaps more
effectively these are perhaps the key to
us bootstrapping our way out of the the
rather serious situation we find
ourselves in people who are conscious of
the fact that the interior is as
important as the exterior
in fact more important right now are
well they're not entirely rare but
finding people who are conscious of that
fact and are also competently and
effectively putting it together with the
exterior and the intellect is rare and
as far as I can tell very important
there's no way that we're going to be
able to do the things we need to do
through using the forms of communication
technique and the forms of mind that we
currently have and so we have to have
some kind of shift and so being able to
be mindful of that work and have some
skillfulness in that and then
experiments they're trying to figure out
how to actually deploy it in context
that give rise to increasing levels of
individual depth and insight is kind of
a fundamentally new thing and is vastly
more helpful than all the various kinds
of conversation that happened in just
kind of a superficial
[Music]
you